Paul Schweikher Papers
Paul Schweikher Papers
1955-1966
Schweikher, Paul, 1903-
16.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American architect. Correspondence, architectural drawings, designs, specifications, and project records relating to Schweikher's practice.
149571
Biographical History
Robert Paul Schweikher (1903-1997) was born in Denver in 1903 and began his architectural training at the University of Colorado in 1921. After moving to Chicago in 1922, he enrolled in architecture and design classes at the The Art Institute of Chicago and then at the Armour Institute of Technology. While studying in Chicago, he also worked at the architectural firm of Lowe and Bollenbacher and, later, with David Adler. He completed his bachelor's degree at the Yale School of Architecture in 1929. After graduation, Schweikher spent a year in European study and travel, funded by a fellowship from Yale. Schweikher returned to Chicago in 1930 and worked for several local architects, including George Fred Keck and Philip Maher. His early reputation as an avant-garde architect was bolstered by his inclusion in the 1933 landmark exhibition on modern architecture at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City. In 1934, he became principal and senior partner in the firm of Lamb and Elting, renamed Schweikher and Elting in 1946. He left that partnership in 1953 to become chairman of the School of Architecture at Yale University, and also established a private practice of residential architecture. In 1958, Schweikher resigned his position at Yale to serve as head of the Deparment of Architecture at Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie-Mellon), retiring from that position in 1970. He subsquently moved to Arizona and opened a small private practice there. Schweikher died in Phoenix in 1997. (portions taken from Art Institute of Chicago interview with Schweikher)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Paul Schweikher Collection contains material relating to Schweikher's professional life during this period. General files, in alphabetical order, comprises correspondence and subject files for institutions and organizations (American Humanist Association, Carnegie Institute of Technology, Pennsylvania Democratic State Committee, Pennsylvania Society of Architecture, Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission, University of Buffalo), fellow architects (Donald Hisaka, Earl P. Carlin, Clovis Heimsath), and specific jobs (Court Place office building, Evanston Unitarian Church, Knoxville Branch Library, New Haven Teachers College, Watertown Library).
The Carnegie Institute of Technology subseries includes detailed material relating to Schweikher's tenure as head of CIT's Department of Architecture, such as course descriptions, curriculum, scholarships, salary and faculty meeting material. The Yale, CT subseries has similar material relating to Schweikher's tenure as chairman of Yale University's School of Architecture.
Related Material
holds the papers of a number of American architects. Please refer to for a full listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Schweikher, Paul, 1903-; Architectural design.; Architectural practice.; Architects -- United States.; Architecture, American.; Architecture -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Architectural records.; Correspondence.; Specifications.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- General files
  - Accounts payable (Box 1)
  - Accounts receivable (Box 1)
  - Albright
    - Accounting (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1958; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Gallery (Box 1)
    - Greek examples (Box 1)
    - Original scheme (Box 1)
  - Allegheny Redevelopment Authority (Box 1)
  - American Academy in Rome (Box 1)
  - American Humanist Association
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Accounting (Box 1)
    - Agreements (Box 1)
    - Codes-sites (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1958; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Designs (Box 1)
    - Estimates (Box 1)
    - Outline specifications (Box 1)
    - Program (Box 1)
  - Architecture exhibit (Box 1)
  - Architectural forum (Box 1)
  - Argonne National Laboratory, IL (Box 1)
  - Arts assembly (Box 1)
  - Arts Club of Chicago (Box 1)
  - B (Box 1)
  - Beal, James H. (Box 1)
  - Bennett, Edward H., Jr. (Box 1)
  - Berg, Stanley E. (Box 1)
  - Bethany College, WV (Box 1)
  - Blue Cross (Box 1)
  - Boston Redevelopment Authority (Box 1)
  - Broughton, Philip (Box 1)
  - Building Research Advisory Board (Box 1)
  - Burhans, Dr. and Mrs. Ernest (Box 1)
  - Burdett, Robert (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - C.I.A.M. - Chermayett (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology
    - Annual reports (Box 2)
    - Art and Civilization (Box 2)
    - Basic Design School (Box 2)
    - Basic Design Symposium (Box 2)
    - Budget (Box 2)
    - Committees (Box 2)
    - Competitions (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Prior to appointment (Box 2)
      - 1956-1966, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Course descriptions (Box 2)
    - Critical reviews (Box 2)
    - Curriculum, 1956-1963; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Department announcement (Box 2)
    - Design (Box 2)
    - Development program (Box 2)
    - Exhibition (Box 2)
    - Faculty meeting (Box 2)
    - Joint planning project (Box 2)
    - Memorandums (Box 2)
    - Museum research (Box 2)
    - Municipal Sports Center (Box 2)
    - Planning (Box 2)
    - President Guyturd (Box 2)
    - Programs, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
    - Salary (Box 2)
    - Scholarships and grants (Box 2)
    - Scholarships and fellowships (Box 2)
    - Statements of expense (Box 2)
    - Student activities (Box 2)
    - Student curricular memoranda (Box 2)
    - Successor to President Warren (Box 2)
    - Trustees list (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate curriculum (Box 2)
    - Urban Design (Box 2)
    - Urban Center Proposal (Box 2)
    - Visiting critics and lectures, 1956-1966; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Visits and travel for C.I.T. by Schweikher (Box 2)
  - Calendar (Box 3)
  - Earl P. Carlin, correspondence (Box 3)
  - Carnegie Institute (Box 3)
  - Carnegie Tech Campus Activities Building
    - Accounting (Box 3)
    - Agreements (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Estimate (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
    - Specifications (Box 3)
  - Campus activities building (Box 3)
  - Carver, Norman F. (Box 3)
  - Catholic University of America, DC (Box 3)
  - Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints (Box 3)
  - Civil Rights Title VII (Box 3)
  - Calvin J. Collins (Box 3)
  - Collins, general (Box 3)
  - Concrete panels (Box 3)
  - Competitions, Roosevelt Memorial (Box 3)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 3)
  - Connecticut, University of
    - Nuclear Reactor (Box 3)
  - Consultants correspondence (Box 3)
  - Contributions (Box 3)
  - Court Place Corporation
    - Sachnoff (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
  - Court Place office building
    - Accounting (Box 3)
    - Agreement (Box 3)
    - Specifications (Box 3)
  - Cox, Felix O. (Box 3)
  - Duquesne University, PA, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Duquesne University, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - E.D.A. (Box 4)
  - East Liverpool
    - Trinity United Presbyterian (Box 4)
    - First Presbyterian Church
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Designs (Box 4)
      - Publicity (Box 4)
  - Eichorn, Robert (Box 4)
  - Eisler Nurseries (Box 4)
  - B.K. Elliot Co. (Box 4)
  - Elting, Winston (Box 4)
  - John Slade Ely (Box 4)
  - Erie Arts Center, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Evanston Unitarian Church
    - General (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1957; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Designs (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Europe trip (Box 5)
  - Exhibitions, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - F (Box 5)
  - Fitch, Elliot G. (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 5)
  - G (Box 5)
  - G.D.T. House (Box 5)
  - Galleries (Box 5)
  - Gates Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - General correspondence (Box 5)
  - General services administration (Box 5)
  - Gensert, miscellaneous correspondence (Box 5)
  - Gettle, Stanley (Box 5)
  - Goodspeed, miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Hoag, E. Keith (Box 5)
  - Hagerstown, Md.
    - Hospital (Box 5)
    - Library (Box 5)
  - Hays, Office supplies (Box 5)
  - Hazard, Leland (Box 5)
  - Heimsath, Clovis (Box 5)
  - Hisaka, Donald M., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Hoffman, Julius (Box 5)
  - Hospitals (Box 5)
  - House and home (Box 5)
  - Hoyt, Edward S. (Box 5)
  - Humanist (Box 5)
  - Roy Hunt, Jr. (Box 5)
  - I (Box 5)
  - Illinois, University of (Box 5)
  - Indiana State Board of Registration for Architects (Box 5)
  - Institute for Applied Technology (Box 5)
  - International Congress on Religion (Box 5)
  - International Union of Architects (Box 5)
  - Interoffice correspondence (Box 5)
  - Interoffice notes (Box 5)
  - Izenour, George (Box 5)
  - J (Box 5)
  - Job record sheets (Box 5)
  - Juries, speaking engagements (Box 5)
  - K (Box 5)
  - Kansas City Hospital, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Kassler, Kenneth (Box 5)
  - Keller house (Box 5)
  - Keller notes (Box 5)
  - Kipplinger Washington Letters (Box 5)
  - Koppers Arhitectural Student Design Competition (Box 5)
  - Knoxville Branch Library
    - Accounting (Box 6)
    - Areas (Box 6)
    - Consultants fees (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Drawings, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Inquiries (Box 6)
    - Landscaping (Box 6)
    - Original specifications (Box 6)
    - Requisitions (Box 6)
    - Shop drawings (Box 6)
    - Supervisions (Box 6)
  - L (Box 6)
  - Law architecture (Box 6)
  - LaTrobe, Pennsylvania (Box 6)
  - Letterheads (Box 6)
  - Life magazine (Box 6)
  - Lunning, Fredrick (Box 6)
  - M (Box 6)
  - Macho Pacho (Box 6)
  - Maine State Cultural Building (Box 6)
  - Maldonado, Tomas (Box 6)
  - Marcus, Edward (Box 6)
  - Maryville, F.A.C. (Box 7)
  - Maryville
    - Chapel (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Furniture (Box 7)
    - Organ (Box 7)
  - Maryville College
    - Chapel (Box 7)
    - Dormitory, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Fine Arts Center (Box 7)
    - Furniture (Box 7)
    - Master plan (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Program notes (Box 7)
  - Maryville master plan (Box 7)
  - Materials and methods (Box 7)
  - A.H. Mathias and Co. (Box 7)
  - Matthews, Jas. H. (Box 7)
  - Mellon Institute (Box 7)
  - Membership cards (Box 7)
  - Memoranda, interoffice (Box 7)
  - Memphis competition (Box 7)
  - Metcalf
    - Agreement (Box 7)
    - Biographical data (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Laurel General Hospital (Box 7)
    - Photographers (Box 7)
    - Somerville Hospital (Box 7)
    - Tufts University (Box 7)
  - Mercy Hospital (Box 7)
  - Methodist Church
    - Brownsville, Pa. (Box 7)
    - Orchard Park, N.Y. (Box 7)
  - Michigan, University of (Box 7)
  - Miles Farnsworth decision (Box 7)
  - Mining, Strip (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Monk, Peter Miller, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Charles Moore (Box 8)
  - N (Box 8)
  - National Council of Architectural Boards (Box 8)
  - National Council of the Arts in Education (Box 8)
  - National Observer (Box 8)
  - Nelson Walker Associates (Box 8)
  - New Haven Teachers College
    - Accounting (Box 8)
    - Agreement (Box 8)
    - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Designs (Box 8)
  - New York State University construction performance criteria development (Box 8)
  - O (Box 8)
  - Office (Box 8)
  - Oregon Shakespearean Festival (Box 8)
  - Olivetti Underwood (Box 8)
  - Paid Bills
    - Blueprinting, 1957-1960; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Business, 1958-1962; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Personal, 1956-1962; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Pan American Health Organization (Box 9)
  - Parents committee (Box 9)
  - Park Forest
    - Accounting, 7 folders (Box 9)
    - Agreements (Box 9)
    - Faith United Protestant Church (Box 9)
  - Payroll information (Box 9)
  - Payroll time sheets (Box 9, 10)
  - Leonard D. Passell (Box 10)
  - Pennsylvania Democratic State Committee (Box 10)
  - Pennsylvania Society of Architecture (Box 10)
  - Pennsylvania State University (Box 10)
  - Petrilli Studios (Box 10)
  - Peru Trip (Box 10)
  - Pittsburgh Plan for Art (Box 10)
  - Pittsburgh Regional Committee for U.N. Urbanization Seminar (Box 10)
  - Pittsburgh Theological Seminary (Box 10)
  - Presbyterian Church, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Princeton, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Print Panels (Box 10)
  - Progressive Architecture (Box 10)
  - Publications (Box 10)
  - R (Box 10)
  - William Rea (Box 10)
  - Records, business, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Rizner, general (Box 11)
  - Homer R. Rizner House (Box 11)
  - Robie House (Box 11)
  - R. Roberts (Box 11)
  - Rogovy House (Box 11)
  - Roselle Property (Box 11)
  - Rosenblum, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - S (Box 11)
  - Saalman, Howard (Box 11)
  - Merle Sachnoff (Box 11)
  - Saint Christopher's Episcopal Church (Box 11)
  - Saint Vincent's College (Box 11)
  - Salem College (Box 11)
  - Schenectady (Box 11)
  - Scholl, Jack (Box 11)
  - Seton Hill College, PA (Box 11)
  - Schwartz, Ken (Box 11)
  - Schweikher, Fredrick (Box 11)
  - Schweikher, Paul
    - Accounting (Box 11)
    - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - House (Box 11)
    - Research (Box 11)
    - Skills (Box 11)
    - Subscriptions (Box 11)
    - Time cards (Box 11)
    - Visiting program (Box 11)
    - Washington, D.C. (Box 11)
  - Sert, Jose Luis (Box 11)
  - Sheps - Casten (Box 11)
  - Sillman, Sewell (Box 11)
  - Smith, Hinchman and Grills (Box 11)
  - Smith, Milton (Box 11)
  - Smith Supplies (Box 11)
  - Snowden, Mrs. C.L., Jr. (Box 11)
  - Somerville, Mass. Hospital (Box 11)
  - Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission (Box 11)
  - Mrs. Dorothy N. Sproul House (Box 11)
  - Sproul House, 1962 (Box 11)
  - Sproul-Loomis Street (Tree House) (Box 11)
  - Summers, Gene R. (Box 11)
  - Swank, Dean Earle R. (Box 11)
  - T (Box 11)
  - Tange, Kenzo (Box 12)
  - Tax, personal income (Box 12)
  - Teaching-Education, A.I.A. (Box 12)
  - Toledo, Ohio (Box 12)
  - Teaneck - Grace Lutheran (Box 12)
  - Telephone and T.A.S. (Paid Bills) (Box 12)
  - Thiel College, PA (Box 12)
  - Three Rivers Art Festival (Box 12)
  - Travel, train, air, hotels, rates, times (Box 12)
  - Thompson, G.D.
    - Accounting (Box 12)
    - Contractors accounting (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 12)
    - Furniture bills (Box 12)
    - New shop drawings (Box 12)
    - Memoranda (Box 12)
  - Travel assignments (Box 12)
  - U (Box 12)
  - Uniontown Library, PA (Box 12)
  - University of Buffalo, 18 folders (Box 12, 13, 14)
  - University of Florida (Box 14)
  - Univeristy of Minnesota (Box 14)
  - University of Vermont (Box 14)
  - Upton House (Box 14)
  - Urban Development of Pittsburgh, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Urban Transportation Planning (Box 14)
  - Urban Design Proposed Program (Box 14)
  - V (Box 14)
  - Mies Van Der Rohe (Box 14)
  - Vassar, NY
    - Accounting, general
      - 1st Scheme, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 2nd Scheme, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Agreements (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1959; 9 folders (Box 14)
  - Designs (Box 14)
  - Estimates (Box 15)
  - Publications (Box 15)
  - Victorian Society (Box 15)
  - W (Box 15)
  - Ward, John B. (Box 15)
  - Watertown Library
    - Accounting (Box 15)
    - Agreements (Box 15)
    - Correspondence (Box 15)
    - Designs (Box 15)
    - Presentation, 1956-1957; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Philip M. Weber, accountant (Box 15)
  - Wechsler, R.L. (Box 15)
  - Western Reserve University, OH (Box 15)
  - Whyte, Lancelot Law (Box 15)
  - Wilkinsburg Housing
    - Accounting (Box 15)
    - Merle Sachnoff (Box 15)
    - Specifications (Box 15)
  - Dr. Craig Wright (Box 15)
  - Y (Box 15)
  - Yale, CT
    - General, 1950s - 60; 21 folders (Box 15)
    - Account Engineering Bldg, 1955-56 (Box 15)
    - Alumni Association (Box 15)
    - Architecture, 1950-56 (Box 15)
    - Department of Architecture
      - Budget, 1953-54 (Box 16)
      - Faculty communications, 1954; undated (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous notes, 1953-54 (Box 16)
      - Prospecture faculty, 1955 (Box 16)
      - Student communications, 1954-56 (Box 16)
      - Visiting critics, 1955-56; 1963 (Box 16)
    - Education, 2nd & 3rd years, 1954-55 (Box 16)
    - Long range plan, 1954-55 (Box 16)
    - News bureau, 1954-55 (Box 16)
    - University Press, 1962-63 (Box 16)
    - Research Center, 1954-56; Accounting (Box 16)